Guide to the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg, Vice President for Academic Affairs, 1963-present UPG.RG.04
ULS Greensburg
University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg, Vice President for Academic Affairs
1963-present
ULS Greensburg
University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg
UPG.RG.04
1 box
Administrative Records of the Vice President for Academic Affairs of the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg, 1963-present.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Custodial History
Transferred from the Office of the Vice President for Academic Affairs to the UPG Archives.
See Also
For Vice President for Academic Affairs Search Committee, See: UPG.RG.36 Ser.: Vice President for Academic Affairs Search Committee, 1995.
Scope and Content Notes
Memoranda, Subject Files, Documents, Dr. Carl F. Poke, Dr. Norman Scanlon, Dr. Mark D. McColloch, Dr. J. Wesley Jamison, Dr. Jacqueline Hamilton Horrall
Historical Note: The office of the Vice President for Academic Affairs evolved from the office of the Dean of Academic Affairs which had its inception with that of the campus of the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg in 1963. Dr. Carl F. Poke was appointed Dean of Academic Affairs in 1963 and remained as Dean until his retirement from the deanship in February, 1991. Dr. Norman W. Scanlon was the associate dean and was appointed interim dean in 1991, dean in 1993, and vice president of academic affairs in 1995 when the name of the office was changed from the Dean of Academic Affairs to that of Vice-President for Academic Affairs.
As of June, 1997, the office of the Vice-President for Academic Affairs had responsibility for the following areas: Admissions and Financial Aid; Divisions of Natural Sciences, Mathematics, and Engineering; Division of Behavioral Sciences; Division of Humanities; Public Relations; Library; Audio-Visual Services; Student Services.
Universities and colleges –- Pennsylvania –- Greensburg –- Records and correspondence; Universities and colleges -– Pennsylvania -– Greensburg -– Administration; University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg
- Dr. Carl F. Poke, 1963-Feb.1991; I.
  - Documents, 1974; 1.
    Scope and Content Notes
    A Proposal to Change the Program at the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg from Lower-To-Upper Division. September, 1974. Photocopy. [Has copies of letters from Jack Freeman to Harold C. Wiser, Assistant Commissioner to Coordinate Higher Education, Dept of Education, Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, dtd Aug. 23, 1974 and to William H. Rea, Chairman of the Board. Of Trustees, Univ. Of Pittsburgh, dtd Aug. 23, 1974.]
    See Also
    See also UPG.RG.70.2 UPO DOC 1974.
    - Documents, 1974 (Museum-cabinet 1, Shelf 1, Box 5)
  - Memoranda, 1972-1989; 2.
    1972 April 7 To: N. McWhinney. Subject: Reading Program for Allan Hudock. [Has attached memorandum from N.H. McWhinney dtd 25 April in reply.]
    1977 September 15 To: Faculty. Subject: Enrollment--Fall Term 1977.
    1988 April 4 To: All Advisors. Subject: Gerontology Certificate.
    1989 [Announcements of openings for full time faculty positions: Communications; Economics; Mathematics; Physical Education; Psychology]
    1989 November 20 To: All Faculty. Subject: Divisional Chairpersons. [3 incumbents to serve another term: Behavioral Sciences--Manhar Vyas; Humanities--Collette Levin; Natural Science and Engineering--Estrella Ang]
    - Memoranda, 1972-1989 (Museum-cabinet 1, Shelf 1, Box 5)
  - Subject Files, 1970-1987; 3.
    - Academic Development of the Greensburg Campus, 1970-77, 1982-83, 1987
      Contains: memo dtd 6/12/70 from C.F. Poke to M. Richard Rose, subject, "An Undergraduate Business Program at Greensburg"; memo dtd 1/18/71 from Charles H. Peake to Presidents Smith, Ball, Swarts, subject, "Policy on Faculty Organizations in Regional Campuses"; document, "Criteria For Appointment and Promotion", dtd 1/20/71 from M.R. Rose; memo 10/20/71 from Albert B. Smith to All Faculty and Staff, subject, "Budget Crisis"; memo from ABS to M.R. Rose dtd 1/28/72, subject, "Expansion of the General Studies Program on the Greensburg Campus", with an attached memo dtd 1/26/72 from C.F. Poke to ABS, subject, "Additional Degree Programs in General Studies at the Greensburg Campus"; memo dtd 11/13/72 from N.H. McWhinney to All Members of the Faculty Senate transmitting memo of 1/25/72 from ABS to Robert Nossen, Assoc. Provost for Regional Campuses, subject, "Possible Directions for the Academic Development of the Greensburg Campus"; memo dtd 2/1/72 from Richard Dapra, Joanne Viano, Manharlal Vyas (Dean's Cabinet Committee for Program Expansion in the School of General Studies) to C.F. Poke and members of the Dean's Academic Cabinet, subject, "Proposal to Institute Degree-Granting Programs in the Humanities and Social Science Areas of Concentration in the School of General Studies at the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg"; memo 4/28/72 from Rhoten A. Smith, Provost, to Chancellor Wesley W. Posvar, subject, "Proposed Satellite Campuses: Pitt East and Pitt West"; memo C.F. Poke to Robert Nossen dtd 6/12/73, subject, "Existence of Business Programs in General Studies at the Greensburg Campus" and includes as an attachment a memo 8/12/71 from Donald H. Henderson to Deans Steel Gow, Arthur Fedel, H.J. Zoffer and Ass't Provost R. Rose, subject, "Undergraduate Business Programs at Greensburg"; memo from Rhoten A. Smith to Dr. Robert Nossen dtd 7/19/73, subject, "Business School Offerings at Greensburg Through the School of General Studies" [authorization to proceed]; memo from W.W. Posvar to Bd. of Trustees dtd 12/24/73, subject, "Redefinition of Missions: The University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg and at Titusville" and which includes a copy of a "A Proposal for Changing the Program at Greensburg Campus from Lower to Upper Division" dtd 12/17/73 and a copy of "A Proposal for Adapting the Mission of the University of Pittsburgh at Titusville" dtd 12/27/73; memo from Jack E. Freeman to Robert Nossen dtd 11/11/74, subject, "Proposed SGS Baccalaureate Programs at Greensburg"; ltr dtd 5/31/77 from Donald H. Henderson, Acting Provost, to Dean Robert D. Marshall, [College of Arts and Sciences should consider courses in Anthropology, economics, English Literature, Geography, Political Science, Psychology, and Sociology taken at the UPG General Studies Center on the same basis as courses in the School of General Studies]; ltr from Dr. Merle J. Moskowitz, Prof. And Assoc. Chairman, Dept. of Psychology to Norman W. Scanlon, Director of Evening Studies, in re a proposed 4-year General Studies major in Psychology at the Greensburg Campus; ltr 7/12/77 from Robert B. Hinman, Chairman, English Dept., to Dr. Donald T. Reilly in re proposal for a major in English at the Greensburg campus; ltr 8/11/77 from Robert S. Walters, Chairman, Dept. of Political Science, to Carl F. Poke in re proposal for a Political Science offering in the School of General Studies at the Greensburg campus; ltr 8/15/77 from Norman W. Scanlon to Dr. J. Steele Gow, Dean of General Studies, in re pursuit of department programs at UPG (Psychology, English Literature, Political Science) with attachments of ltrs from Dr. Merle J. Moskowitz (Psychology), Robert B. Hinman (English), Robert S. Walters (Political Science); ltr dtd 8/22/77 from Steel Gow to N.W. Scanlon [acknowledges receipt of departmental letters of approval for Psychology, English Literature and Political Science majors and extends the Dean's approval as well]; memo 6/1/82 from Andrew R. Blair and Edward J. Palascak to Dr. Robert Nossen, subject, "Memorandum of Understanding Concerning the CGS Management Major at the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg"; memo 6/14/82 from Steele Gow to Norman W. Scanlon [approval of the CGS Administrative Committee for the proposed Applied Mathematics major for the CGS degree at Greensburg] and has attached a ltr 6/1/82 from W.E. Deskins, Chairman of Mathematics and Statistics to Dean Carl Poke [approval of a proposal by Dr. Mary Grace O'Donnell for a CGS four-year degree program in Applied Mathematics at UPG] and a ltr from N.W. Scanlon to Dr. Steele Gow in re proposal by M.G. O'Donnell for an Applied Mathematics major]; memo from Steele Gow dtd 1/31/83 to Carl Poke, subject, "Natural Science Concentration"; ltr 3/28/87 from Edwin F. Ochester, director, Writing Program to N.W. Scanlon in re [writing program at UPG].
      - Academic Development of the Greensburg Campus, 1970-77, 1982-83, 1987 (Museum-cabinet 1, Shelf 1, Box 5)
    - Enrollment, 1963-1966
      Contains: Memo dtd 1/20/64 ABS to M.R. Rose in re "Enrollment Figures for 1st and 2nd Trimesters, 1963-1964" and includes "Budget Planning Data" requested by MRR; Memo of CFPoke dtd 9/9/64 to ABS and C Kuhn, "Number of Students and number of Credit Hours, Sept. 1963, Sept. 1964; Document, [Enrollment 1965/66 [freshmen, sophomores, full time total; Part-time (day & evening); Graduate; Total part-time day/evening.
      - Enrollment, 1963-1966 (Museum-cabinet 1, Shelf 1, Box 5)
    - Faculty, 1965-1966
      Contains: Document dtd 8/30/65 in re "Faculty Profile" and gives names of faculty member, subject taught, rank, degrees, instituions granting degrees, teaching experience, salary, comments; Document "Faculty Analysis, Fall Term 1966" and gives name of faculty member, rank, salary, work load, degrees, institutions granting degrees.
      - Faculty, 1965-1966 (Museum-cabinet 1, Shelf 1, Box 5)
- Dr. Norman W. Scanlon, Feb.1991-June 2000; II.
  - Memoranda, 1993-2000; 1.
    1993 August 23, 30 in re: "Duplicating Procedures/Restrictions for FY 1994." Attached: copy of memo. 8/30/93 from Don Reilly to all full-time Humanities Faculty.
    1994 March 17 in re: UPG Five-Year Plan.
    1995 June 8 Ltr from James V. Maher, Provost to Dr. Norman Scanlon, Vice President for Academic Affairs, UPG. Subject: [approval of proposal to establish a major in Communication: Rhetoric and Communication at the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg (UP-G).]
    1995 October 16 from Norm Scanlon to All Full-Time Faculty. Subject: Self-Study for the Evaluation of UPG's Academic Programs. [Gives names of members of the University Faculty invited by the Provost to serve on the internal review team. Transmits a copy of the self-study document. For document See: DOCUMENTS1995, October. A Self-Study... For another copy See: RG02.2 Series: DOCUMENTS. 1995 October A Self-Study...)
    1997 December 8 To: UPG Staff, Librarians, Academics Heads. From: Dr. Norman Scanlon, Dr. Guy Rossetti. Subject; [annual staff recognition luncheon]. [List individuals with 25, 10, and 5 years of service]
    1997, Sept. 30. From: Norm Scanlon. To: Dr. Frank Cassell. Subject: Draft Statement Re: Academic Council.
    1997, Oct. 7. To: Dr. Norman Scanlon, Vice Pres. For Academic Affairs, et al. From: Frank A. Cassell, President. Subject: Establishment of the UPG Academic Council.
    1998, January 27. To: Carol Calloway and Alicia Covarrubias. Subj.: Possible Art Exhibit in Millstein Library. [in re the possibility of an art exhibit in the Millstein Library featuring works that are currently at Chatham College. Discussed at senior staff meeting and were in agreement that this is appropriate use of academic space and that it would not be disruptive of normal library operations; this kind of activity should not become the responsibility of Dr. Duck or of the members of the library staff. sets conditions, i.e., transportation insurance, hanging/arranging, insurance when the exhibit is on campus, security arrangements, any special lighting, etc.]
    1998 January 29 Subject: installation of Dr. Cassell
    1998 August 24 From Dr. Norm Scanlon and Rick Fogle. Subject: National Honor Societies.
    1999 October 21 To: Rich Blevins, Tracy Douthett, Pat Duck, Wes Jamison, Bill Martin, Mark McColloch, Mary Grace O'Donnell. Subject: Data on Retention, Graduation, and Persistence Rates for UPG Assessment Project. [Tables: Headcount Enrollment of First-time, Full-time Freshmen, University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg, Entrance Years 1990-1998 [by ethnic group]; Retention Rates of First-time, Full-time Freshmen, University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg, Entrance Years 1990-1997 [by ethnic group]; Persistence Rates of First-time, Full-time Freshmen, University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg, Entrance Years 1990-1994 (by ethnic group)]
    1999 November 17. To: Rich Blevins, Wes Jamison, Mark McColloch, Mary Grace O'Donnell. Subject: Enrollment by Discipline.
    2000 January 19 To: All Faculty and Staff. [promotion of Dr. Mark McColloch to Associate Vice President for Academic Affairs]
    - Memoranda, 1993-2000 (Museum-cabinet 1, Shelf 1, Box 5)
  - Memoranda (Addendeum), 1991, 1992, 1996-1999; 2.
    7.23.91, Evaluation Process; 12/15/92, Weather emergency; 3/1/96, Internal Rev. Team Conducting Academic Program Evaluation; 9/4/97, Use of FOB Conference room; 10/27/97, United Way II; 11/12/97, Books by the Faculty; 6/15/98, Positions Announcement [Student Svcs. Specialists II]; 2/26/98, Position Annoucement (Faculty Secretarial Position-- Sec. II); 3/18/98, Use of Staff Lounge on 3/25; 4/30/98 To: Dr. Frank A. Cassell. Subject: Some Thoughts on Quality and Markers of Excellence. 5p.; 3/8/99, Candidates for Vice President of Administrative Affairs; 4/1/99, National Honor Societies.]
    - Memoranda (Addendeum), 1991, 1992, 1996-1999 (Museum-cabinet 1, Shelf 1, Box 5)
  - Planning and Budget Committee [UPG Planning and Budget Committee], 1998-2004; 3.
    Contents: Memo dtd. 12/4/98 from MDM in re meeting of December 11 for the purpose of discussing a proposed new History major, i.e. "a proposal to establish a baccalureate program in History"; memo dtd 10/15/99 from N. Scanlon, Subject: "Proposed Certificate Program in Latin American Studies"; draft of FY00 [Budget] Planning Document; Memo dtd 2/19/04 Subject: Brief Meeting 2/25 to review draft of this year's [FY 2004] campus plan.
    - Planning and Budget Committee [UPG Planning and Budget Committee], 1998-2004 (Museum-cabinet 1, Shelf 1, Box 5)
  - Documents, 1984-1997; 4.
    1984, June. University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg Long-Range Planning Policies 1985-90. Phase I. Planning Document June 1984. 58 p. [bd. vol.]
    [1994] Long-Range Plan, University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg. 31p. + [8p.] Appendices: competitor institutions; peer institutions; part-time students, 1991; direct and referral applications/deposits; funding sources-capital goals; comparative data -- UPG and other Provost's area schools/colleges; funding-academic and administrative goals
    1995, October. A Self-Study for the Evaluation of Academic Programs at the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg. October, 1995. 130 p.
    1997 [February 25, 1997, Revised, September 15, 1997]. "Evaluation of the Academic Programs of the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg: Summary Report and Recommendations of the Subcommittee for the Evaluation of the Academic Programs." Includes: Memorandum dtd 22 October 1997 From: NWS To Academic Council, Subject: "Draft Response to Provost Re: Program Review Recommendations".
    - Documents, 1984-1997 (Museum-cabinet 1, Shelf 1, Box 5)
- Dr. Mark D. McColloch, July 2000-June 2003; III.
  - Documents, July 18, 2007; 1.
    Proposal for a BS Degree in Chemistry at the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg.
    - Documents, July 18, 2007 (Museum-cabinet 1, Shelf 1, Box 5)
- Dr. Norman W. Scanlon, June 2003-June 2006; IV.
  - Memoranda, Mar. 23/24 2005; 1.
    To: All Full-Time Faculty. Subject: Classroom Visitation Policy. [Encloses a copy of the classroom visitation policy that was adopted by Senate several years ago. Per the discussion at the Senate meeting of 3/21/05.]
    - Memoranda, Mar. 23/24 2005 (Museum-cabinet 1, Shelf 1, Box 5)
- Dr. J. Wesley Jamison, July 2006-June 2016; V.
- Dr. Jacqueline Hamilton Horrall, July 2016-present; VI.
  - Memoranda, 2016; 1.
    2016, March 21. SPS to Faculty and Staff. Subject: New Vice President for Academic Affairs Announced. [Dr. Jacqueline Hamilton Horrall will become Vice President for Academic Affairs beginning July 1, 2016. She replaces Dr. J. Wesley Jamison who is stepping down from that position.]
    2016, May 18. JMHorrall To: LASzypulski, PJHoch, VAKubenko. Subject: Letter to Faculty announcing formation of a committee to evaluate the candidates for the Assistant Vice President for Academic Affairs position. In addition to Wes Jamison, [J.M. Horrall]. Committee members are still Bill Rued, Ben Espinoza, and Frank Wilson. Hope to announce new AVPAA by June 5.
    2016, June 3. JMH to Colleagues. Subject: The New Assistant VPAA. [Three faculty members interviewed to fill the vacancy of Assistant Vice President for Academic Affairs. Dean Nelson accepted the offer to become VPAA effective Sept. 1, 2016. He will continue to act as Division Chair of the Natural Sciences until the end of the Fall semester.]
    2016, July 18. JMH to Faculty and Staff. Announces the selection of Beth Tiedemann as Director of Academic Advising and Registrar as of August, 2016. (Search Committee: Bill Rued, Mary Anne Koleny, Sheila Confer, Brandy Darr.)
    2016, Sept. 13. JMH to Faculty and Staff. Subject: ["...current task divisions and implied reporting structure in Academic Affairs..."]
    2016, Oct. 24 JH to All Faculty. Subj.: Division Chairs--Behavioral and Natural Sciences. [Appointment of Mark Stauffer as Division Chair of the Division of Natural Sciences, Mathematics, and Engineering and Paul Adams as Chair of the Behavioral Sciences Division. Term of MS to begin January 2017; PA term to begin July 2017.]
    - Memoranda, 2016 (Museum-cabinet 1, Shelf 1, Box 5)